If you want to be successful as a personal
trainer or any other similar business,
you're going to need to master these five
things.
And if you miss just one of these things,
you could end up working way more hours
for way less money
and probably burning out.
A part of me dies inside every time I meet
someone who goes, "Oh, I used to be a
personal trainer." Used to be.
Manage your own hours,
choose what you want to
learn. Wear activewear all the time.
No one stops personal training
or a similar business unless they just
couldn't get new clients. Kind of sad,
really.
But my name's James Smith,
it's my mission to help small businesses
get more
clients so they don't have to go back to
recruitment, because I've done it.
It's terrible.
The first of those very important key
elements is what I'm going to
call in-person mastery.
First lesson that's really important
is the hours
that you do in person as a coach,
whether physio, PT, yoga instructor,
they're actually your least paid hours in
the scale of the next 10 years, but you
learn the most in that period,
that's going to help you earn more.
In essence,
although the personal training sessions
that I took 10 years ago didn't
pay that well,
I'm still monetizing now because I got to
learn the people, their problems,
their issues.
There are things people say to you in
person that they just don't say online.
There are things
that you pick up on people in person
that you just don't learn
online. And the craziest thing
is so many people
are looking to bypass this step
because they think they're too good for
in-person clients.
But you're literally stepping over such a
golden opportunity that you won't even
see the returns for for a few years.
It's really important
that you learn people,
you learn your demographic, because
you need to understand their problems.
Because everyone sits down in the
consultation and says, "Oh,
I'd like to be a
little bit fitter, and
I would like to feel a bit..." It's
bullshit.
When you really get to know that person,
five sessions in, they're like, "My wife
left me,
I want to get a hotter version." Correct.
Another woman says,
"I stood up in a meeting in front of some
important people, and
a bit of my belly fat stuck out from my
dress, and I'm mortified by it." Okay,
cool. Some people say,
"My best friend's getting married
and I want to look better
than her at her wedding." Awesome.
And these little things
that you learn from your clients in person
then become your
hooks and your setups and verbiage
that you can use in your content.
I don't know if that's a real word.
But then there's another element of
in-person
mastery. When your client comes in
and you just sense they're a little bit
off,
they're exhausted, their kid's ill,
or it's quarter end,
and you start to pick up
on the frustrations
and the elements of their programming
where they need a break
or a downturn. Then as an online coach,
you can go, "Hey, Trish.
The last couple of weeks we've not seen
much of a performance increase.
I recommend we have a de-load week next
week. Tell me about your work setup.
Are you working towards a quarter end?
Have you been doing more than usual?
Is there stress you've maybe not told me
about?" It's only through picking up those
issues in person,
then you can have the same spider senses
when you work with
people online.
And these little things add up in most to
client retention.
People stay with you longer because they
get all these little instances of you
understanding that person.
And one of the biggest things
that people overlook from
not wanting to work with people in person
or thinking they're too good for it, is
how many ideas you get from your clients.
I'll never forget,
one of my first videos that ever went out,
my client said,
"James, I know it's kind of embarrassing,
but I don't really understand macros.
What are they?" I was like, "Wow,
that would make such a good video." So I
helped
the client. I went away
and made the video.
Then when another client came back and
was like, "What's macros?" I was like,
"You'll never guess what, Sheila.
I actually made a video about that.
Check it out." So don't overlook in-person
mastery.
The more time you can spend there,
the more you're setting yourself up for
success.
Imagine in-person mastery being like the
foundations you're building to build a
skyscraper on.
If you just go out there trying to
skyscraper without
foundations, you could fall down.
Which brings me on to number two,
time management.
Now, this isn't so much being on time.
Tardiness? Is that the word? I don't know.
Do you know what tardiness means? Yeah,
of course you don't.
It's a word.
Of course you don't. How old are you?
Tardiness, the quality
or fact of being late.
Lateness. There you go. Keep
that in the edit.
They can have that one for free, Declan.
First of all,
if you're going to be late for people...
When I say time management,
I'm not talking about being on time.
You should be on time to every single
session, you little fucker.
What I'm talking about
is managing your time in the business
and on the business.
In the business is serving the sessions,
walking the floor, being in the gym
physically. On the business
is maybe time at home with your laptop
out, making your
website, your landing page,
working on your email marketing platform,
strategizing
maybe the content you're going to do for
the week. In the business gets you paid.
On the business will get you paid down the
line.
Now, unfortunately,
a lot of people just spend time in the
business, and then after
30 years, they stop work or they burn out,
and then they have nothing set up and
they kind of go back to recruitment.
Whereas if you can spend more time on the
business strategizing these next few
moves and going, "Hmm,
if I did this for three years,
maybe I could give up working
on the gym floor and have something set up
for me." It's about managing your time
there.
There are going to have to be quite a few
unpaid hours that you start
implementing now,
so you can get some really well-paid hours
in a few years' time.
So we've got time in the business,
time on the business,
which then brings us to
the schedule. In the beginning,
you should pretty much say yes to every
single
session you can,
but very soon you should start actually
trying to allocate session
times that people attend to.
You have a 6:00, you have a 7:00.
Then you have an 8:15 and a 9:15.
Then you have a half-hour break,
and you might
have an 11:00 and a 12:00. Whatever.
Stick to the hours,
create some organization,
and go from chaos into structure.
If you stay at chaos,
you will be in the gym too long.
There'll be too many gaps in between
clients, and ultimately,
you just won't have a
life,
and you'll end up going back to
recruitment, because you go, "Oh, I just
couldn't bear being in the gym all day."
You didn't have to be there if you'd
managed your diary a bit better. There
are setting boundaries for your hours.
And within your first three to six months
as a coach, you should stop probably
working evenings. I know people go,
"But James, 5:00 p.m. and 6:00 p.m.
is my bread and butter." Listen,
I don't want to charge people loads of
money to
come into the gym at 5:30 p.m.
when the gym is swamped
and I've got a queue of
three people to use the leg press. No,
thanks.
The evening is disgusting in the gym,
and the worst part
is you've been awake for
14 hours. So in time, it's important
that you want to eradicate evening
sessions
and actually bring your finish time
earlier and earlier and earlier.
You can make a lot of money as an
in-person PT and never do a session after
2:00 or
3:00 p.m.
And if you can create the demand for your
businesses, you can do that
quite soon. Then
that means you're spending less time in
the gym, more time at
home, more time on the business,
more time with your partner,
your loved one, your
girlfriend, your family,
and more time even to go to the cafe
and have a nice 3:00
p.m. coffee and sit down
and write some emails
that you're going to send out
tomorrow morning on a schedule.
Whatever it is.
But if you are a trap to your diary,
you are fucked from the off.
So many people fall into the trap of being
a slave to the hours, thinking that they
need to accept every session,
accept every time,
bend over backwards for their
clients. "Oh,
can we do two hours later today?" "Sure,
I'll just sit in the gym for
another four or five hours." No,
it's not happening.
You wouldn't message your dentist on the
day going, "I'm going to be two hours
late.
Is that okay?" You wouldn't do it to your
barber, so don't expect people to
do it to you.
If you can manage your time effectively As
a coach
in the gym, you can make your daily,
weekly, monthly life
so much better and so much more effective.
Which brings me on to number three,
business priorities.
One of the first traps
that people fall into is thinking
that they should be
working for free rent.
The majority of gyms that go, "Hey,
you can work for
free in the gym,
you just got to work for us a little bit."
If you deduct the
amount of money that they save you off
your rent and divide it by the amount of
hours that you're doing, you
are working for minimum wage.
If you're a coach,
the last thing you want to do
is work anywhere near minimum
wage, let alone try
and charge people a large amount of money
for your
services.
Then they come in on a lunch break
and see you wiping down someone's
sweat off a leg press. It's not happening.
You are better off paying it, because
that is a business expense which you
can then deduct against your tax bill.
If something is reducing your
profitability,
it is also reducing your tax
bill.
You are better off halving those hours,
because those 12 hours a week that
you're wiping down sweat from the leg
press or walking around working for the
gym,
you could be spending in your business
or on your business, which are both hugely
profitable. Some now,
some further down the line.
The gym does not have your best interests
at heart.
It has the best interest of the gym.
And getting you to do your little PT
business, but better yet, do slave
labor around the gym
and do the bitchy tasks like putting bog
roll in the toilets
when someone's had a shit
and used it all up,
is much more there for their benefit
than yours. Pay to play. Pay your money,
get the most out of it.
I could be making this video at home,
but instead, I'll spend £2,000 a month on
this warehouse. Why? Because one,
my business is paying for this, not me.
Two, it's a tax reduction.
It's probably money
that would go to the government
anyway. And three,
this expense permits me to make better
content, which benefits my business,
my content, everything.
See it the same way with what you do.
Don't look to cut costs
when it comes to facility.
If it's expensive,
it's probably because it's good.
Do not work for anyone for minimum wage.
You're supposed to be a fitness
professional.
When it comes to business priorities,
a lot of people don't really know how much
they should be charging for an hour.
They go, "How much
are you charging in Wigan for a PT
session?"
ChatGPT,
how much does the average personal trainer
charge in Wigan for a...
That's not how we figure this out.
When it comes to determining your hourly
rate,
unfortunately,
you have to start right at the bottom,
and the only way that can
move up is through demand.
I've got people saying, "Oh,
I've only got three people
as online clients." How much do you
charge? "55 pounds a week." Cool.
You're too expensive, bro. They go,
"What do you mean?
I've got a BSc in Kinesiology,
I've got my SNC." I go, "Whoa, whoa, whoa.
I don't care about your qualifications.
I don't care about how long you've been a
coach.
I don't care about how many IFBB pro cards
you've got.
You're too expensive,
and I know because you've got three
fucking clients." If you
weren't too expensive,
you would have more clients.
And in the onset, what we want
is to be busy for less money,
so then we have the
opportunity and the leverage to increase
our prices over time.
If you want to become an expensive coach,
you start as a cheap coach.
You build demand,
and you slowly increase your prices over
time.
Like putting a frog in hot water.
If you put a frog in hot water,
it will jump out.
But if you put a frog in cold water
and heat it up slowly,
it will boil to death.
That is actually a theory.
It's been debunked,
but the sentiment of the story
should remain the same.
We want to get in cold water,
heat it up slowly through
demand that we can create from social
media and other places.
When it comes to increasing your prices,
your key leverage here is demand.
Someone says, "Oh, James, why
are you putting my prices up?" Because I'm
too busy.
Same with my mentorship. In what? Two
and a bit weeks,
I'm increasing the prices by
$500. Why? Because I need more money? No.
Because I'm too busy.
For me, by increasing the price,
less people join.
Less people join, less work.
The less people join at more money,
more money,
less work. Now, if I was pretty quiet,
I'd probably run a
discount, but I'm not. It's demand
is the leverage.
Same way you want to go on holiday. Oh,
Easter's coming up.
Oh, how much is a flight to Dubai? Oh,
£750. I don't know.
Declan, it's been a
while since I've flown economy.
What does a flight cost in economy these
days?
He doesn't know because he's flown
business, the cheeky cunt.
Insert whatever an economy flight is.
Oh, no way.
UK economy. [gags] No, I'm only joking.
I used to fly Air China. Just like... Oi,
humble brag. Keep this in the edit.
Still got a sticker in my passport from
when I used to fly Air China to save £100.
Beijing, 10-hour stop-off.
Don't worry about it. Anyway, demand.
Easter.
You're thinking, oh,
I know how much a flight is.
Not on Easter it's not.
Double it. Why?
Because everyone wants to fly at Easter.
Some say you're better off in the UK.
You pull your kids out of school,
you get a fine.
That fine will be less than trying to fly
the kids during the holiday.
So pull them out, pay the school,
cheaper flight, cheaper hotel. Anyway.
Again, within this section,
we're going to look at how to negotiate
prices.
Golden rule.
This could be a whole video in itself.
If someone's not willing to pay you the
amount that you want, instead of moving
your price down, make the session shorter.
Everyone knows an hour
is about 5 to 10 minutes too long for a PT
session anyway.
The perfect PT session
is like 30 to 45 minutes.
So if someone wants to do 30 minutes,
they can do their own warm-up.
They can do their own biceps
and triceps at the end.
You go there for the main compounds.
The main reason is
that person just coming to the gym
and seeing you for half an
hour is half the battle. They go, "Oh,
I didn't have a 2 for Tuesday's Domino's
last night because I'm seeing my PT
tomorrow." So never come down on prices,
just
come down on session price.
And then some people are like, "Oh, James,
I'm a
student. Can you do me a discount?" No,
but I can give you a half-hour session
twice a week. Cool. Now, in their mind,
they're still paying the full hourly rate,
but they're getting two sessions.
Me, I'm still only giving them an hour,
and it's more time in the gym, more
coverage for other people to see me
and potentially want to use me.
Then one of the other things that's
important within this business
is delegation.
I could do this edit. I'm good at editing.
I'm fire at editing.
But Declan over there just so happens to
be better.
Now,
some of the audio in this video might drop
in and out because my car is
being detailed outside,
and even though he got here at 8:00 a.m.
and it's now 11,
he decided now to use the pressure washer.
So although we're going to clean up the
audio in post-production, for me, paying
him to clean my car means
that I'm not cleaning my car.
And if I'm not cleaning my car,
do you know what I am?
Making content for my channel.
So some of your business priorities should
be
getting other people to do things
that you don't want to do,
because by doing so,
it means you can do things that
are more important to your business.
Like make this video with the sole purpose
of getting you to buy my PT starter kit
course,
which there'll be a link in the
description.
But let's not get distracted because we
need to talk and move on to the next area,
social media priorities.
Using social media
is like an interest savings account.
If you pay into this for a few years,
your money is just going to
compound and get bigger and bigger
and bigger because your audience
is going to
compound.
The people invested in your brand
and business are going to compound.
If you put money in an ISA hoping to be
rich in a year, yeah, fat But if
you see the long game,
people overestimate what they can do in
months and very much
underestimate what they can do in years.
So see it like that.
For the majority of you,
short-form content is the way
that you want to
emerge, because long-form is exhausting,
it's tiring, it's expensive to edit.
You just don't have the time because
you're a coach.
So utilize short-form content because it
just takes one video to completely change
your scenario. And wow, what's that?
Imagine if I was to give you my short-form
content creation course included in the
PT Starter Kit. Well, don't worry,
it's already in the description.
But don't click on that yet,
we've got more things to cover off.
Be sure to be looking to create content
which can be used as a resource to send
clients to. Someone goes, "Oh, James,
I'm struggling with this." "Don't worry, I
made a video." "Oh, James,
sorry about this." "Don't worry,
I've made a video."
"Oh, James,
I'm not sure about my pricing." "Don't
worry, I've made a video." A
video isn't just an asset
that we float on the internet to get new
people to come
into our ecosystem.
We can also use it to send our existing
clients to.
"Oh, James,
I'm struggling with this." "Don't worry,
I've created a resource for
it. Here's the YouTube link,
here's the Instagram link,
here's whatever it is." So
content isn't just for today,
for the next 24 hours.
It's a place that we can send people to
when they're struggling and that we can
repost. Another social media priority
is about building an email list.
I don't care if it's your first 1
subscriber, 10 subscribers,
100 subscribers.
You need to start the email list.
You cannot push that back any further.
The longer you put it back,
the more you're just going to be at a
flipping back of
the queue when the race takes off.
Email marketing is so important.
The day you start social media
is the day you start email marketing,
because you
create an incentive structure to build
your email list through social media.
And another social media priority
is going to be about creating gravitas.
Some form of authority in a space where
people go, "Oh, my God, watch
that person's content because they know
what they're on about." And moving into
five to wrap up quickly, brand priorities.
Not many people, especially coaches,
are considering their brand with all of
this.
My advice, contrarianism.
Be a contrarian in one area where
you go against the grain,
you disagree with people openly.
Then there's polarization. Don't try
and appease everyone.
You want to make sure
that you have an approach.
Like for me,
I drop the C-bomb quite a lot because I
know that 70% of
people are going to go,
"Absolutely disgusting language to be
using
online." And other people are going to go,
"That's my type of guy." The mustache.
As a single man,
I would have this in all the time because
70% of women would go,
"Mate, you look like a pedo.
Why have you got such a deep voice for a
woman?" Also,
if I was a pedo,
that's the last thing that I'd be repping.
But then 30% of women go,
"I like the mo." Again,
it's not about pleasing everyone,
it's about pleasing that subset.
Do the same with your content
and your brand.
One of the biggest hiccups you're going to
have as a coach or in a similar industry
is worrying about what other people think
about you.
So you're a personal trainer, you go, "Oh,
fuck.
Oh,
what do other personal trainers think of
me?" You're a mortgage broker, "What
do other mortgage brokers think of me?"
Or you might be an author, "What are other
authors...?" Your peers
are the only people that
are never going to buy your
product. Never, ever, ever.
So don't worry about their input
or their opinion,
because quite literally,
they're the only people that
are never going to buy your
product. And the reason
that all these things we've spoken about
are so important
is that down the line you will diversify.
You might not be a personal trainer in
five years.
You might be doing something completely
different.
You might end up writing a book,
which I never knew I'd write a book until
I ended
up writing a book.
You might end up bringing out a drinks
business, which
will hit eight figures this year.
So make sure that you
are building your socials, your gravitas,
your email list, so
that down the line
when you do want to have a little bit of a
change, you are set
up for that. Now,
if this video tickled your pickle in any
way, that short-form
content creation course and
that PT Starter Kit combined
are 99 US dollars, which
is an absolute steal. Like I said,
there's going to be a link in the
description
for that. Please check it out, buy it.
Could revolutionize your life
or might not,
but I put all the nuggets in there.
And if you're still not convinced to give
me your money, then check out this video
here because YouTube is a smart bugger
and it thinks that if you enjoyed that
video,
that you would absolutely love this one.
And if you don't want to watch that,
I'm not going to force you because I'm not
your dad. You have a good day.